DAVID SONTAG: So we're done with
our segment on causal inference
and reinforcement learning.
And for the next week,
today and Tuesday's lecture,
we'll be talking about
disease progression
modeling and disease subtyping.
This is, from my perspective,
a really exciting field.
It's one which has really a
richness of literature going
back to somewhat
simple approaches
from a couple of decades ago up
to some really state of the art
methods, including
one which is in one
of your readings
for today's lecture.
And I could spent a few weeks
just talking about this topic.
But instead, since we have a lot
to cover in this course, what
I'll do today is give
you a high-level overview
of one approach to try to
think through these questions.
The methods in today's lecture
will be somewhat simple.
They're meant to illustrate
how simple methods can
go a long way.
And they're meant
to illustrate, also,
how one could learn
something really
significant about
clinical outcomes
and about predicting
these progression
from these simple methods.
And then in Tuesday's lecture,
I'll ramp it up quite a bit.
And I'll talk about several
more elaborate approaches
towards this problem,
which tackle some more
substantial problems that
we'll really elucidate
at the end of today's lecture.
So there's three
types of questions
that we hope to answer when
studying disease progression
modeling.
At a high level, I
want you to think
about this type of
picture and have
this in the back of your
head throughout today
and Tuesday's lecture.
What you're seeing here is
a single patient's disease
trajectory across time.
On the x-axis is time.
On the y-axis is some
measure of disease burden.
So for example, you could
think about that y-axis
as summarizing the amount of
symptoms that a patient is
reporting or the amount of pain
medication that they're taking,
or some measure of what's
going on with them.
And initially, that disease
burden might be somewhat low,
and maybe even the patient's
in an undiagnosed disease
state at that time.
As the symptoms get worse
and worse, at some point
the patient might be diagnosed.
And that's what I'm
illustrating by this gray curve.
This is the point in
time which the patient is
diagnosed with their disease.
At the time of diagnosis, a
variety of things might happen.
The patient might
begin treatment.
And that treatment
might, for example,
start to influence
the disease burden.
And you might see a drop in
disease burden initially.
This is a cancer.
Unfortunately, often we'll
see recurrences of the cancer.
And that might manifest
by a uphill peak
again, where it is burden grows.
And once you start
second-line treatment,
that might succeed in
lowering it again and so on.
And this might be a cycle that
repeats over and over again.
For other diseases for which
have no cure, for example,
but which are managed
on a day-to-day basis--
and we'll talk about
some of those--
you might see, even on a
day-by-day basis, fluctuations.
Or you might see nothing
happening for a while.
And then, for example,
in autoimmune diseases,
you'll see these flare-ups where
the disease burden grows a lot,
then comes down again.
It's really inexplicable
why that happens.
So the types of questions that
we'd like to really understand
here are, first, where is
the patient in their disease
trajectory?
So a patient comes in today.
And they might be
diagnosed today
because of symptoms somehow
crossing some threshold
and them coming into
the doctor's office.
But they could be
sort of anywhere
in this disease trajectory
at the time of diagnosis.
And a key question is, can we
stage patients to understand,
for example, things
like, how long are they
likely to live based on what's
currently going on with them?
A second question is, when
will the disease progress?
So if you have a patient
with kidney disease,
you might want to
know something about,
when will this patient kidney
disease need a transplant?
Another question is, how will
treatment effect that disease
progression?
That I'm sort of
hinting at here,
when I'm showing these
valleys that we conjecture
to be affected by treatment.
But one often wants to ask
counterfactual questions like,
what would happen to this
patient's disease progression
if you did one treatment
therapy versus another treatment
therapy?
So the example that I'm
mentioning here in this slide
is a rare blood cancer
named multiple myeloma.
It's rare.
And so you often
won't find data sets
with that many patients in them.
So for example,
this data set which
I'm listening in the very bottom
here from the Multiple Myeloma
Research Foundation
CoMMpass study
has roughly 1,000 patients.
And it's a publicly
available data set.
Any of you can
download it today.
And you could study questions
like this about disease
progression.
Because you can look at
laboratory tests across time.
You could look at when
symptoms start to rise.
You have information about what
treatments a patient is on.
And you have
outcomes, like death.
So for multiple myeloma,
today's standard
for how one would attempt
to stage a patient
looks a little bit like this.
Here I'm showing you two
different staging systems.
On the left is a
Durie-Salmon Staging System,
which is a bit older.
On the right is what's called
the Revised International
Staging System.
A patient walks into
their oncologist's office
newly diagnosed with
multiple myeloma.
And after doing a
series of blood tests,
looking at quantities such as
their hemoglobin rates, amount
of calcium in the
blood, also doing,
let's say, a biopsy of
the patient's bone marrow
to measure amounts of different
kinds of immunoglobulins,
doing gene expression
assays to understand
various different
genetic abnormalities,
that data will then feed into
a staging system like this.
So in the Durie-Salmon
Staging System,
a patient who is in
stage one is found
to have a very low
M-component production rate.
So that's what I'm
showing over here.
And that really corresponds to
the amount of disease activity
as measured by their
immunoglobulins.
And since this is
a blood cancer,
that's a very good
marker of what's
going on with the patient.
So at sort of this
middle stage, which
is called neither stage
one nor stage three,
is characterized
by, in this case--
well, I'm not going
to talk with that.
If you go to stage
three for here,
you see that the M-component
levels are much higher.
If you look at X-ray studies
of the patient's bones,
you'll see that there are
lytic bone lesions, which
are caused by the disease
and really represent
an advanced status
of the disease.
And if you were to measure
for the patient's urine
the amount of
light-chain production,
you see that it has much
larger values as well.
Now, this is an
older staging system.
In the middle, now I'm showing
you a newer staging system,
which is both
dramatically simpler
and involves some
newer components.
So for example, in stage one, it
looks at just four quantities.
First it looks at
the patient's albumin
and beta-2 microglobulin levels.
Those are biomarkers that can be
easily measured from the blood.
And it says no
high-risk cytogenetics.
So now we're starting to
bring in genetic quantities
in terms of quantifying
risk levels.
Stage three is characterized
by significantly higher
beta-2 microglobulin
levels, translocations
corresponding to particular
high-risk types of genetics.
This will not be the focus
of the next two lectures,
but Pete is going to
go much more detail
in two genetic aspects
of precision medicine
in a week and a half now.
And in this way, each
one of these stages
represents something
about the belief
of how far along the patient
is and is really strongly used
to guide treatment therapy.
So for example, patient
is in stage one,
an oncologist might
decide we're not going
to treat this patient today.
So a different type of question,
whereas you could think about
this as being one
of characterizing
on a patient-specific level--
one patient walks in.
We want to stage that
specific patient.
And we're going to look
at some long-term outcomes
and look at the
correlation between stage
and long-term outcomes.
A very different question is
a descriptive-type question.
Can we say what will the typical
trajectory of this disease look
like?
So for example, we'll talk
about Parkinson's disease
for the next couple of minutes.
Parkinson's disease is a
progressive nervous system
disorder.
It's a very common one, as
opposed to multiple myeloma.
Parkinson's affects over 1 in
100 people, age 60 and above.
And like multiple myeloma, there
is also disease registries that
are publicly available and
that you could use to study
Parkinson's.
Now, various
researchers have used
those data sets in the past.
And they've created
something that
looks a little bit like
this to try to characterize,
at now a population
level, what it
means for a patient to
progress through their disease.
So on the x-axis,
again, I have time now.
On the y-axis, again,
it denotes some level
of disease disability.
But what we're
showing here now are
symptoms that might arise at
different parts of the disease
stage.
So very early in
Parkinson's, you
might have some sleep behavior
disorders, some depression,
maybe constipation, anxiety.
As the disease gets
further and further along,
you'll see symptoms such as mild
cognitive impairment, increased
pain.
As the disease goes further on,
you'll see things like dementia
and an increasing amount
of psychotic symptoms.
And information like
this can be extremely
valuable for a patient who is
newly diagnosed with a disease.
They might want to make
life decisions like,
should they buy this home?
Should they stick with
their current job?
Can they have a baby?
And all of these
questions might really
be impact-- the answer
to those questions
might be really impacted by
what this patient could expect
their life to be like over
the next couple of years,
over the next 10 years
or the next 20 years.
And so if one could
characterize really well what
the disease trajectory
might look like,
it will be incredibly valuable
for guiding those life
decisions.
But the challenge is that--
this is for Parkinson's.
And Parkinson's is
reasonably well understood.
There are a large
number of diseases
that are much more rare,
where any one clinician might
see a very small number of
patients in their clinic.
And figuring out, really, how
do we combine the symptoms that
are seen in a very noisy fashion
for a small number of patients,
how to bring that together to
a coherent picture like this
is actually very,
very challenging.
And that's where some
of the techniques we'll
be talking about in
Tuesday's lecture,
which talks about how do
we infer disease stages,
how do we automatically
align patients across time,
and how do we use very
noisy data to do that,
will be particularly valuable.
But I want to emphasize
one last point regarding
this descriptive question.
This is not about prediction.
This is about understanding,
whereas the previous slide
was about prognosis,
which is very much
a prediction-like question.
Now, a different type of
understanding question
is that of disease subtyping.
Here, again, you might be
interested in identifying,
for a single patient, are they
likely to progress quickly
through their disease?
Are they likely to progress
slowly through their disease?
Are they likely to
respond to treatment?
Are they not likely to
But we'd like to be able to
characterize that heterogeneity
across the whole
population and summarize it
into a small number of subtypes.
And you might think about
this as redefining disease
altogether.
So today, we might say patients
who have a particular blood
abnormality, we will say are
multiple myeloma patients.
But as we learn more
and more about cancer,
we increasingly understand that,
in fact, every patient's cancer
is very unique.
And so over time, we're going
to be subdividing diseases,
and in other cases combining
things that we thought
were different diseases,
into new disease categories.
And in doing so it will allow us
to better take care of patients
by, first of all, coming
up with guidelines
that are specific to each
of these disease subtypes.
And it will allow us to
make better predictions
based on these guidelines.
So we can say a patient
like this, in subtype A,
is likely to have the
following disease progression.
A patient like
this, in subtype B,
is likely to have a
different disease progression
or be a responder
or a non-responder.
So here's an example of
such a characterization.
This is still sticking with
the Parkinson's example.
This is a paper from a
neuropsychiatry journal.
And it uses a
clustering-like algorithm,
and we'll see many more examples
of that in today's lecture,
to characterize patients
into, to group patients into,
four different clusters.
So let me walk you
through this figure
so you see how to interpret it.
Parkinson's patients
can be measured in terms
of a few different axes.
You could look at their
motor progression.
So that is shown here
in the innermost circle.
And you see that
patients in Cluster 2
seem to have intermediate-level
motor progression.
Patients in Cluster 1 have very
fast motor progression, means
that their motor symptoms
get increasingly worse
very quickly over time.
One could also look at
the response of patients
to one of the drugs,
such as levodopa
that's used to treat patients.
Patients in Cluster
1 are characterized
by having a very poor
response to that drug.
Patients in Cluster
3 are characterized
as having intermediate,
patients in Cluster 2
as having good
response to that drug.
Similarly one could look
at baseline motor symptoms.
So at the time the
patient is diagnosed
or comes into the clinic
for the first time
to manage their
disease, you can look
at what types of motor-like
symptoms do they have.
And again, you see different
heterogeneous aspects
to these different clusters.
So this is one means-- this is
a very concrete way, of what I
mean by trying to
subtype patients.
So we'll begin our journey
through disease progression
modeling by starting out
with that first question
of prognosis.
And prognosis, from
my perspective,
is really a supervised
machine-learning problem.
So we can think about prognosis
from the following perspective.
Patient walks in at time zero.
And you want to know
something about what
will that patient's disease
status be like over time.
So for example, you
could ask, at six months,
what is their disease status?
And for this patient, it might
be, let's say, 6 out of 10.
And where these
numbers are coming from
will become clear
in a few minutes.
12 months down the line,
their disease status
might be 7 out of 10.
18 months, it might
be 9 out of 10.
And the goal that
we're going to try
to tackle for the first
half of today's lecture
is this question of,
how do we take the data,
what I'll call the x vector,
available for the patient
at baseline and
predict what will
be these values at
different time points?
So you could think about that as
actually drawing out this curve
that I showed you earlier.
So what we want to do is
take the initial information
we have about the
patient and say, oh,
the patient's disease status, or
their disease burden, over time
is going to look a
little bit like this.
And for a different
patient, based
on their initial covariance,
you might say that their disease
burden might look like that.
So we want to be able to
predict these curves in this--
for this presentation,
there are going
to actually be sort of
discrete time points.
We want to be able
to predict that curve
from the baseline information
we have available.
And that will give
us some idea of how
this patient's going to
progress through their disease.
So in this case
study, we're going
to look at Alzheimer's disease.
Here I'm showing you two
brains, a healthy brain
and a diseased brain, to really
emphasize how the brain suffers
under Alzheimer's disease.
We're going to characterize
the patient's disease status
by a score.
And one example of such
a score is shown here.
It's called the Mini
Mental State Examination,
summarized by the acronym MMSE.
And it's going to
look as follows.
For each of a number of
different cognitive questions,
a test is going to
be performed, which--
for example, in the middle,
what it says is registration.
The examiner might name three
objects like apple, table,
penny, and then ask the patient
to repeat those three objects.
All of us should be able to
remember a sequence of three
things so that when we
finish the sequence,
you should be able
to remember what
the first thing in
the sequence was.
We shouldn't have a
problem with that.
But as patients get
increasingly worse
in their Alzheimer's
disease, that task
becomes very challenging.
And so you might give 1.4
correct for each correct.
And so if the patient gets all
three, if they repeat all three
of them, then they
get three points.
If they can't remember
any of them, zero points.
Then you might continue.
You might ask something else
like subtract 7 from 100,
then repeat some
results, so some sort
of mathematical question.
Then you might return back to
that original three objects
you asked about originally.
Now it's been, let's
say, a minute later.
And you say, what
were those three
objects I mentioned earlier?
And this is trying to get
at a little bit longer-term
memory and so on.
And one will then
add up the number
of points associated with
each of these responses
and get a total score.
Here it's out of 30 points.
If you divide by 3, you get
the story I give you here.
So these are the
scores that I'm talking
about for Alzheimer's disease.
They're often characterized
by scores to questionnaires.
But of course, if you had done
something like brain imaging,
the disease status
might, for example,
be inferred automatically
from brain imaging.
If you had a smartphone device,
which patients are carrying
around with them, and which
is looking at mobile activity,
you might be able to
automatically infer
their current disease
status from that smartphone.
You might be able to infer it
from their typing patterns.
from their email or Facebook
habits.
And so I'm just
trying to point out,
there are a lot
of different ways
to try to get this number
of how the patient might be
doing at any one point in time.
Each of those an
interesting question.
For now, we're just going
to assume it's known.
So retrospectively,
you've gathered this data
for patients, which is now
longitudinal in nature.
You have some
baseline information.
And you know how
the patient is doing
over different
six-month intervals.
And we'd then like to be able
to predict to those things.
Now, if this were--
we can now go back in time to
lecture three and ask, well,
how could we predict
these different things?
So what are some approaches
that you might try?
Why don't you talk to your
neighbor for a second, and then
I'll call on a random person.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
OK.
That's enough.
My question was
sufficiently under-defined
that if you talk
longer, who knows
what you'll be talking about.
Over here, the two of you--
the person with the computer.
Yeah.
How would you
tackle this problem?
AUDIENCE: Me?
OK.
DAVID SONTAG: No, no, no.
Over here, yeah.
Yeah, you.
AUDIENCE: I would
just take, I guess,
previous data, and then--
yeah, I guess, any
previous data with records
of disease progression over
that time span, and then treated
[INAUDIBLE].
DAVID SONTAG: But
just to understand,
would you learn five
different models?
So our goal is to get these--
here I'm showing
you three, but it
might be five different numbers
at different time points.
Would you learn one
model to predict
what it would be at
six months, another
to predict what
would be a 12 months?
Would you learn a single model?
Other ideas?
Somewhere over in
this part of the room.
Yeah.
You.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID SONTAG: Yeah.
Sure.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID SONTAG: So use a
multi-task learning approach,
where you try to learn all
five at that time and use what?
What was the other thing?
AUDIENCE: So you can learn to
use these datas in six months
and also use that as your
baseline [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID SONTAG: Oh, that's
a really interesting idea.
OK.
So the suggestion was--
so there are two different
suggestions, actually.
The first suggestion was do a
multi-task learning approach,
where you attempt
to learn-- instead
of five different and sort
of independent models,
try to learn them
jointly together.
And in a second,
we'll talk about why
it might make sense to do that.
The different thought was, well,
is this really the question
you want to solve?
For example, you
might imagine settings
where you have the
patient not at time zero
but actually at six months.
And you might want
to know what's
going to happen to
them in the future.
And so you shouldn't just
use the baseline information.
You should recondition
on the data
you have available for time.
And a different way of
thinking through that is you
could imagine learning
a Markov model,
where you learn something
about the joint distribution
of the disease stage over time.
And then you could, for
example, even if you only
had baseline
information available,
you could attempt
to marginalize over
the intermediate values
that are unobserved to infer
what the later values might be.
Now, that Markov model approach,
although we will talk about it
extensively in the
next week or so,
it's actually not a very good
approach for this problem.
And the reason why is because
it increases the complexity.
So when you are
learn-- in essence
if you wanted to predict
what's going on at 18 months,
and if, as an intermediate
step to predict what goes on
at 18 months, you
have to predict
what's going to go
on at 12 months,
and then the likelihood of
transitioning from 12 months
to 18 months, then
you might incur error
in trying to predict what's
going on at 12 months.
And that error is then
going to propagate
as you attempt to think about
the transition from 12 months
to 18 months.
And that propagation of
error, particularly when
you don't have
much data, is going
to really hurt the [INAUDIBLE]
of your machine learning
algorithm.
So the method I'll be
talking about today
is, in fact, going
to be what I view
as the simplest possible
approach to this problem.
And it's going to be
direct prediction approach.
So we're directly
going to predict
each of the different
time points independently.
But we will tie
together the parameters
of the model, as was suggested,
using a multi-task learning
approach.
And the reason why
we're going to want
to use a multi-task
learning approach
is because of data sparsity.
So imagine the
following situation.
Imagine that we had just
binary indicators here.
So let's say patient is
OK, or they're not OK.
So the data might
look like this--
0, 0, 1.
Then the data set
you might have might
look a little bit like this.
So now I'm going to
show you the data.
And one row is one patient.
Different columns are
different time points.
So the first patient, as I
showed you before, is 0, 0, 1.
Second patient
might be 0, 0, 1, 0.
Third patient might
be 1, 1, 1, 1.
Next patient might
be 0, 1, 1, 1.
So if you look at the
first time point here,
you'll notice that you have
a really imbalanced data set.
There's only a single 1
in that first time point.
If you look at the second
time point, there are two.
It's more of a
balanced data set.
And then in the
third time point,
again, you're sort of back
into that imbalanced setting.
What that means is
that if you were
to try to learn from just
one of these time points
by itself, particularly in the
setting where you don't have
that many data points
alone, that data sparsity
and in outcome label is
going to really hurt you.
It's going to be
very hard to learn
any interesting signal just
from that time point alone.
The second problem is that
the label is also very noisy.
So not only might you
have lots of imbalance,
but there might be noise in
the actual characterizations.
Like for this patient,
maybe with some probability,
you would calculate 1, 1, 1, 1.
With some other probability,
you would observe 0, 1, 1, 1.
And it might correspond
to some threshold in that
score I showed you earlier.
And just by chance, a
patient, on some day,
passes the threshold.
On the next day, they might
not pass that threshold.
So there might be a lot of
noise in the particular labels
at any one time point.
And you wouldn't want that noise
to really dramatically affect
your learning algorithm
based on some,
let's say, prior
belief that we might
have that there might be
some amount of smoothness
in this process across time.
And the final problem is that
there might be censoring.
So the actual data
might look like this.
For much later time
points, we might
have many fewer observations.
And so if you were to
just use those later time
points to learn your
predictive model,
you just might not
have enough data.
So those are all
different challenges
that we're going to
attempt to solve using
a multi-task learning approach.
Now, to put some
numbers to these things,
we have these four
different time points.
We're going to have 648 patients
at the six-month time interval.
And at the four-year
time interval,
there will only be 87 patients
due to patients dropping out
of the study.
So the key idea here will be,
rather than learning these five
independent models,
we're going to try
to jointly learn the parameters
corresponding to those models.
And the intuitions
that we're going
to try to incorporate
in doing so
are that there might
be some features that
are useful across these five
different prediction tasks.
And so I'm using the example of
biomarkers here as a feature.
Think of that like a
laboratory test result,
for example, or an answer to
a question that's available
baseline.
And so one approach
to learning is
to say, OK, let's
regularize the learning
of these different
models to encourage
them to choose a common
set of predictive features
or biomarkers.
But we also want to allow
some amount of flexibility.
For example, we might want to
say that, well, at any one time
point, there might be
couple of new biomarkers
that are relevant for
predicting that time point.
And there might be some small
amounts of changes across time.
So what I'll do right now
is I'll introduce to you
the simplest way to think
through multi-task learning,
which--
I will focus specifically
on a linear model setting.
And then I'll show you
how we can slightly
modify this simple approach to
capture those criteria that I
have over there.
So let's talk about
a linear model.
And let's talk about regression.
Because here, in the example
I showed you earlier,
we were trying to
pick the score that's
a continuous value number.
We want to try to predict it.
And we might care about
minimizing some loss function.
So if you were to try to
minimize a squared loss,
imagine a scenario where you
had two different prediction
problems.
So this might be time
point 0, and this
might be time point 12, for
six months and 12 months.
You can start by summing
over the patients,
looking at your
mean squared error
at predicting what I'll say
is the six-month outcome label
by some linear
function, which, I'm
going to have it as subscript
6 to denote that this
is a linear model for
predicting the six-month time
point value, dot-producted
with your baseline features.
And similarly, your loss
function for predicting,
this one is going be the same.
But now you'll be
predicting the y12 label.
And we're going to
have a different weight
vector for predicting that.
Notice that x is the same.
Because I'm assuming
in everything
I'm telling you here that
we're going to be predicting
from baseline data alone.
Now, a typical approach and try
to regularize in this setting
might be, let's say, to
do L2 regularization.
So you might say,
I'm going to add
onto this some lambda times
the weight vector 6 squared.
Maybe-- same thing over here.
So the way that I set this
up for you so far, right now,
is two different independent
prediction problems.
The next step is to
talk about how we could
try to tie these together.
So any idea, for those of
you who have not specifically
studied multi-task
learning in class?
So for those of you
who did, don't answer.
For everyone else,
what are some ways
that you might try to
tie these two prediction
problems together?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Maybe you could share
certain weight parameters,
so if you've got a
common set of biomarkers.
DAVID SONTAG: So maybe you could
share some weight parameters.
Well, I mean, the simplest way
to tie them together is just
to say, we're going to--
so you might say,
let's first of all
add these two objective
functions together.
And now we're
going to minimize--
instead of minimizing just--
now we're going to minimize over
the two weight vectors jointly.
So now we have a single
optimization problem.
All I've done is I've
now-- we're optimizing.
We're minimizing
this joint objective
where I'm summing this
objective with this objective.
We're minimizing it with respect
to now two different weight
vectors.
And the simplest thing to
do what you just described
might be to say, let's
let W6 equal to W12.
So you might just add in
this equality constraint
saying that these two weight
vectors should be identical.
What would be wrong with that?
Someone else, what
would be wrong with--
and I know that wasn't
precisely your suggestion.
So don't worry.
AUDIENCE: I have a question.
DAVID SONTAG: Yeah.
What's your question?
AUDIENCE: Is x-- are
those also different?
DAVID SONTAG: Sorry.
Yeah.
I'm missing some
subscripts, right.
So I'll put this in superscript.
And I'll put subscript
i, subscript i.
And it doesn't matter for the
purpose of this presentation
whether these are
the same individuals
or different individuals
across these two problems.
You can imagine they're
the same individual.
So you might imagine
that there are
n individuals in the data set.
And we're summing
over the same n
people for both of
these sums, just
looking at different
outcomes for each of them.
This is the six-month outcome.
This is the 12-month outcome.
Is that clear?
All right.
So the simplest thing to do
would be just to not-- now
that we have a joint
optimization problem,
we could constrain the two
weight vectors to be identical.
But of course, this is
a bit of an overkill.
This is like saying that
you're going to just learn
a single prediction problem,
where you sort of ignore
the difference between
six months and 12 months
and just try to predict--
you put those under
there and just
predict them both together.
So you had another
suggestion, it sounded like.
AUDIENCE: Oh, no.
You had just asked
why that was not it.
DAVID SONTAG: Oh, OK.
And I answered that.
Sorry.
What could we do differently?
Yeah, you.
AUDIENCE: You could
maybe try to minimize
the difference between the two.
So I'm not saying that
they need to be the same.
But the chances that they're
going to be super, super
different isn't really high.
DAVID SONTAG: That's a
very interesting idea.
So we don't want
them to be the same.
But I might want them to be
approximately the same, right?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
DAVID SONTAG: And what's
one way to try to measure
how different these two are?
AUDIENCE: Subtract them.
DAVID SONTAG: Subtract
them, and then do what?
So these are vectors.
So you--
AUDIENCE: Absolute value.
DAVID SONTAG: So it's not
absolute value of a vector.
What can you do to turn a
vector into a single number?
AUDIENCE: Take the
norm [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID SONTAG: Take a norm of it.
Yeah.
I think what you meant.
So we might take the norm of it.
What norm should we take?
AUDIENCE: L2?
DAVID SONTAG: Maybe the L2 norm.
OK.
And we might say we want that.
So if we said that this was
equal to 0, then, of course,
that's saying that they
have to be the same.
But we could say that
this is, let's say,
bounded by some epsilon.
And epsilon now is a
parameter we get to choose.
And that would then
say, oh, OK, we've
now tied together these
two optimization problems.
And we want to encourage that
the two weight vectors are not
that far from each other.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: You represent
each weight vector as--
have it just be duplicated
and force the first place
to be the same and the
second ones to be different.
DAVID SONTAG: You're suggesting
a slightly different way
to parameterize this
by saying that W12
is equal to W6 plus
some delta function,
some delta difference.
Is that you're suggesting?
AUDIENCE: No, that you have
your-- say it's n-dimensional,
like each vector
is n-dimensional.
But now it's going
to be 2n-dimensional.
And you force the
first n dimensions
to be the same on
the weight vector.
And then the others, you--
DAVID SONTAG: Now, that's
a really interesting idea.
I'll return to that
point in just a second.
Thanks.
Before I return to
that point, I just
want to point out this isn't the
most immediate think optimize.
Because this is now a
constrained optimization
problem.
What's our favorite algorithm
for convex optimization
in machine learning, and
non-convex optimization?
Everyone say it out loud.
AUDIENCE: Stochastic
gradient descent.
DAVID SONTAG: TAs are
not supposed to answer.
AUDIENCE: Just muttering.
DAVID SONTAG:
Neither are faculty.
But I think I
heard enough of you
say stochastic gradient descent.
Yes.
Good.
That's what I was expecting.
And well, you could do
projected gradient descent.
But it's much easier to
just get rid of this.
And so what we're going
to do is we're just
going to put this into
the objective function.
And one way to do that--
so one motivation would
be to say we're going
to take the Lagrangian
of this inequality.
And then that'll bring
this into the objective.
But you know what?
Screw that motivation.
Let's just erase this.
And I'll just say
plus something else.
So I'll call that lambda 1,
some other hyper-parameter,
times now W12 minus W6 squared.
Now let's look to
see what happens.
If we were to push this
lambda 2 to infinity,
remember we're minimizing
this objective function.
So if lambda 2 is
pushed to infinity,
what is the solution of
W12 with respect to W6?
Everyone say it out loud.
AUDIENCE: 0.
DAVID SONTAG: I said
"with respect to."
So there, 1 minus other is 0.
Yes.
Good.
All right.
So it would be forcing
them that they be the same.
And of course, if
lambda 2 is smaller,
then it's saying we're going
to allow some flexibility.
They don't have to be the same.
But we're going to
penalize their difference
by the squared difference
in their norms.
So this is good.
And so you raised a really
interesting question, which
I'll talk about now,
which is, well, maybe you
don't want to enforce all of
the dimensions to be the same.
Maybe that's too much.
So one thing one could
imagine doing is saying,
we're going to only enforce
this constraint for--
[INAUDIBLE] we're only
going to put this penalty
in for, let's say, dimensions--
trying to think the
right notation for this.
I think I'll use this notation.
Let's see if you guys like this.
Let's see if this notation
makes sense for you.
What I'm saying is I'm
going to take the--
d is the dimension.
I'm going to take the first half
of the dimensions to the end.
I'm going to take that vector
and I'll penalize that.
So it's ignoring the first
half of the dimensions.
And so what that's
saying is, well, we're
going to share parameters for
some of this weight vector.
But we're not going
to worry about-- we're
going to let them be
completely dependent
of each other for the rest.
That's an example of
what you're suggesting.
So this is all great and dandy
for the case of just two time
points.
But what do we do if then
we have five time points?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: There's some
percentage of shared entries
in that vector.
So instead of saying these
have to be in common,
you say, treat all
of them [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID SONTAG: I think you
have the right intuition.
But I don't really know
how to formalize that just
from your verbal description.
What would be the simplest
thing you might think of?
I gave you an example of
how to do, in some sense,
pairwise similarity.
Could you just easily
extend that if you
have more than two things?
You have idea?
Nope?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID SONTAG: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: And then I'd
get y1's similar to y2,
and y2 [INAUDIBLE] y3.
And so I might just--
DAVID SONTAG: So
you might say w1
is similar to w2.
w2 is similar to w3.
w3 is similar to w4 and so on.
Yeah.
I like that idea.
I'm going to generalize
that just a little bit.
So I'm going to start
thinking now about graphs.
And we're going to now define a
very simple abstraction to talk
about multi-task learning.
I'm going to have a graph where
I have one node for every task
and an edge between
tasks, between nodes,
if those two tasks, we want
to encourage their weights
to be similar to another.
So what are our tasks here?
W6, W12.
So in what you're
suggesting, you
would have the following graph.
W6 goes to W12 goes to W24
goes to W36 goes to W48.
Now, the way that we're
going to transform
a graph into an
optimization problem
is going to be as follows.
I'm going to now suppose
that I'm going to let--
I'm going to define a graph
on V comma E. V, in this case,
is going to be the set
6, 12, 24, and so on.
And I'll denote
edges by s comma t.
And E is going to refer
to a particular two tasks.
So for example, the task of
six, predicting at six months,
and the task of
predicting at 12 months.
Then what we'll do is we'll
say that the new optimization
problem is going to
be a sum over all
of the tasks of the loss
function for that task.
So I'm going to ignore what is.
I'm just going to simply write--
over there, I have two
different loss functions
for two different tasks.
I'm just going to
add those together.
I'm just going to leave
that in this abstract form.
And then I'm going to now sum
over the edges s comma t in E
in this graph that I've just
defined of Ws minus Wt squared.
So in the example that I go
over there in the very top,
there were only two
tasks, W6 and W12.
And we had an edge between them.
And we penalized it
exactly in that way.
But in the general
case, one could imagine
many different solutions.
For example, you could
imagine a solution
where you have a complete graph.
So you may have
four time points.
And you might penalize
every pair of them
to be similar to one another.
Or, as was just
suggested, you might
think that there might be
some ordering of the tasks.
And you might say
that you want that--
instead of a complete
graph, you're
going to just have a
chain graph, where,
with respect to
that ordering, you
want every pair of
them along the ordering
to be close to each other.
And in fact, I think
that's probably
the most reasonable thing to
do in a setting of disease
progression modeling.
Because, in fact, we
have some smoothness type
prior in our head
about these values.
The values should be
similar to one another
when they're very
close time points.
I just want to mention
one other thing, which
is that from an
optimization perspective,
if this is what you
had wanted to do,
there is a much cleaner
way of doing it.
And that's to
introduce a dummy node.
I wish I had more colors.
So one could instead
introduce a new weight vector.
I'll call it W. I'll just
call it W with no subscript.
And I'm going to say that
every other task is going to be
connected to it in that star.
So here we've
introduced a dummy task.
And we're connecting
every other task to it.
And then, now you'd
have a linear number
of these regularization
terms in the number of tasks.
But yet you are not
making any assumption
that there exists some ordering
between them in the task.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: Do you--
DAVID SONTAG: And W is never
used for prediction ever.
It's used during optimization.
AUDIENCE: Why do you need a
W0 instead of just doing it
based on like W1?
DAVID SONTAG: Well, if
you do it based on W1,
then it's basically saying
that W1 is special in some way.
And so everything sort
of pulled towards it,
whereas it's not clear that
that's actually the right thing
to do.
So you'll get different answers.
And I'd leave that as
an exercise for you
to try to derive.
So this is the
general idea for how
one could do multi-task
learning using linear models.
And I'll also leave it
as an exercise for you
to think through how you
could take the same idea
and now apply it to, for
example, deep neural networks.
And you can believe
me that these ideas
do generalize in the ways that
you would expect them to do.
And it's a very
powerful concept.
And so whenever you
are tasked with--
when you tackle
problems like this,
and you're in settings
where a linear model might
do well, before you believe that
someone's results using a very
complicated approach is
interesting, you should ask,
well, what about the
simplest possible multi-task
learning approach?
So we already
talked about one way
to try to make
the regularization
a bit more interesting.
For example, we could attempt
to regularize only some
of the features' values
to be similar to another.
In this paper, which was
tackling this disease
progression modeling problem
for Alzheimer's, they
developed a slightly more
complicated approach,
but not too much
more complicated,
which they call the convex
fused sparse group lasso.
And it does the same
idea that I gave here,
where you're going to
now learn a matrix W.
And that matrix W is
precisely the same notion.
You have a different
weight vector per task.
You just stack them
all up into a matrix.
L of W, that's just what I
mean by the sum of the loss
functions.
That's the same thing.
The first term in the
optimization problem,
lambda 1 times the L1 norm
of W, is simply saying--
it's exactly like
the sparsity penalty
that we typically see when
we're doing regression.
So it's simply saying
that we're going
to encourage the weights
across all of the tasks
to be as small as possible.
And because it's
an L1 penalty, it
adds the effect of actually
trying to encourage sparsity.
So it's going to push things
to zero wherever possible.
The second term in this
optimization problem,
this lambda 2 RW squared,
is also a sparsely penalty.
But it's now pre-multiplying
the W by this R matrix.
This R matrix, in this
example, is shown by this.
And this is just one way to
implement precisely this idea
that I had on the board here.
So what this R matrix is
going to say it is it's
going to say for--
it's going to have one--
you can have as many
rows as you have edges.
And you're going to have-- for
the corresponding task which
is S, you have a 1.
For the corresponding task
which is T, you have a minus 1.
And then if you multiply this
R matrix by W transpose, what
you get is precisely these
types of pair-wise comparisons
out, the only difference being
that here, instead of using
a L2 norm, they penalized
using an L1 norm.
So that's what that second term
is, lambda 2 RW transposed.
It's simply an implementation
of precisely this idea.
And that final term is
just a group lasso penalty.
It's nothing really
interesting happening there.
I just want to comment--
I had forgotten to mention this.
The loss term is going to
be precisely a squared loss.
This F refers to
a Frobenius norm,
because we've just
stacked together
all of the different
tasks into one.
And the only interesting
thing that's happening here
is this S, which we're doing
an element-wise multiplication.
What that S is is simply
a masking function.
It's saying, if we don't observe
a value at some time point,
like, for example, if either
this is unknown or censored,
then we're just
going to zero it out.
So there will not be any loss
for that particular element.
So that S is just
the mask which allows
you to account for the fact
that you might have some missing
data.
So this is the approach used
in that KDD paper from 2012.
And returning now to
the Alzheimer's example,
they used a pretty simple
feature set with 370 features.
The first set of features
were derived from MRI scans
of the patient's brain.
In this case, they just derived
some pre-established features
that characterize the amount
of white matter and so on.
That includes some
genetic information,
a bunch of cognitive scores.
So MMSE was one example
of an input to this model,
at baseline is critical.
So there are a number
of different types
of cognitive scores that
were collected at baseline,
and each one of those makes
up some feature, and then
a number of laboratory
tests, which I'm just
noting as random numbers here.
But they have some significance.
Now, one of the most interesting
things about the results
is if you compare the
predictive performance
of the multi-task approach
to the independent regressor
approach.
So here we're showing
two different measures
of performance.
The first one is some
normalized mean squared error.
And we want that to
be as low as possible.
And the second one is
R, as in R squared.
And you want that to
be as high as possible.
So one would be
perfect prediction.
On this first column here,
it's showing the results
of just using independent
regressors-- so if instead
of tying them together with that
R matrix, you had R equal to 0,
for example.
And then in each of
the subsequent columns,
it shows now learning with
this objective function, where
we are pumping up increasingly
high this lambda 2 coefficient.
So it's going to be asking
for more and more similarity
across the tasks.
So you see that even with a
moderate value of lambda 2,
you start to get
improvements between
this multi-task
learning approach
and the independent regressors.
So the average R
squared, for example,
goes from 0.69 up to 0.77.
And you notice how we have 95%
confidence intervals here as
well.
And it seems to be significant.
As you pump that
lambda value larger,
although I won't comment about
the statistical significance
between these columns,
we do see a trend,
which is that performance gets
increasingly better as you
encourage them to be
closer and closer together.
So I don't think I want
to mention anything
else about this result.
Is there a question?
AUDIENCE: Is this
like a holdout set?
DAVID SONTAG: Ah, thank you.
Yes.
So this is on a holdout set.
Thank you.
And that also reminded
me of one other thing
I wanted to mention, which is
critical to this story, which
is that you see these results
because there's not much data.
If you had a really
large training set,
you would see no difference
between these columns.
Or, in fact, if you
had a really data set,
these results would be worse.
As you pump lambda higher,
the results will get worse.
Because allowing flexibility
among the different tasks
is actually a
better thing if you
have enough data for each task.
So this is particularly valuable
in the data-poor regime.
When it goes to try to
analyze the results in terms
of looking at the
feature importances
as a function of
time, so one row
here corresponds to the weight
vector for that time point's
predictor.
And so here we're just looking
at four of the time points,
four of the five time points.
And the columns correspond
to different features that
were used in the predictions.
And the colors correspond to
how important that feature
is to the prediction.
You could imagine
that being something
like the norm of the
corresponding weight
in the linear model, or a
normalized version of that.
What you see are some
interesting things.
First, there are some
features, such as these,
where they're important at
all different time points.
That might be expected.
But then there also
might be some features
that are really important
for predicting what's
going to happen right
away but are really
not important to predicting
longer-term outcomes.
And you start to see
things like that over here,
where you see that, for
example, these features are not
at all important for predicting
in the 36th time point
but were useful for the
earlier time points.
So from here, now
we're going to start
changing gears a little bit.
What I just gave
you is an example
of a supervised approach.
Is there a question?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
If a faculty member
may ask this question.
DAVID SONTAG: Yes.
I'll permit it today.
AUDIENCE: Thank you.
So it's really two questions.
But I like the linear model,
the one where Fred suggested,
better than the
fully coupled model.
Because it seems more
intuitively plausible to--
DAVID SONTAG: And indeed,
it's the linear model
which is used in this paper.
AUDIENCE: Ah, OK.
DAVID SONTAG: Yes.
Because you noticed how that
R was sort of diagonal in--
AUDIENCE: So it's-- OK.
The other observation is that,
in particular in Alzheimer's,
given our current state
of inability to treat it,
it never gets better.
And yet that's not
constrained in the model.
And I wonder if it
would help to know that.
DAVID SONTAG: I think that's
a really interesting point.
So what Pete's
suggesting is that you
could think about this as--
you could think about putting
an additional constraint in,
which is that you can imagine
saying that we know that, let's
say, yi6 is typically less
than yi12, which is typically
less than yi24 and so on.
And if we were able to do
perfect prediction, meaning
if it were the case
that your predicted
y's are equal to your
true y's, then you
should also have that W6 dot xi
is less than W12 dot xi, which
should be less than W24 dot xi.
And so one could imagine
now introducing these
as new constraints in
your learning problem.
In some sense, what
it's saying is,
well, we may not
care that much if we
get some errors in
the predictions,
but we want to make
sure that at least
we're able to sort the
patients correctly,
a given patient correctly.
So we want to ensure at
least some monotonicity
in these values.
And one could easily
try to translate
these types of constraints
into a modification
to your learning algorithm.
For example, if you
took any pair of these--
let's say, I'll take
these two together.
One could introduce
something like a hinge loss,
where you say you want that--
you're going to add a new
objective function, which
says something
like, you're going
to penalize the max
of 0 and 1 minus--
and I'm going to
screw up this order.
But it will be
something like W--
so I'll derive it correctly.
So this would be W12 minus
W24 dot product with xi,
we want to be less than 0.
And so you could look
at how far from 0 is it.
So you could look at W12--
do, do, do.
You might imagine
a loss function
which says, OK, if it's greater
than 0, then you have problem.
And we might penalize it at,
let's say, a linear penalty
however greater than 0 it is.
And if it's less than 0,
you don't penalties at all.
So you say something like
this, max of W12 minus W24
dot product xi.
And you might add
something like this
to your learning objective.
That would try to encourage--
that would penalize violations
of this constraint using a
hinge loss-type loss function.
So that would be
one approach to try
to put such constraints into
your learning objective.
A very different
approach would be
to think about it as a
structured prediction
problem, where instead of
trying to say that you're
going to be predicting a
given time point by itself,
you want to predict the
vector of time points.
And there's a whole
field of what's
called structured prediction,
which would allow one
to formalize objective
functions that might encourage,
for example, smoothness
in predictions across time
that one could
take advantage of.
But I'm not going to go more
into that for reasons of time.
Hold any more questions
to the end of the lecture.
Because I want to make sure I
get through this last piece.
So what we've
talked about so far
is a supervised
learning approach
to trying to predict what's
going to happen to a patient
given what you know at baseline.
But I'm now going to talk
about a very different style
of thought, which is using
an unsupervised learning
approach to this.
And there are going
to be two goals
of doing unsupervised learning
for tackling this problem.
The first goal is
that of discovery,
which I mentioned at the very
beginning of today's lecture.
We might not just be
interested in prediction.
We might also be interested
in understanding something,
getting some new insights
about the disease,
like discovering
that there might be
some subtypes of the disease.
And those subtypes might
be useful, for example,
to help design new
clinical trials.
Like maybe you want to
say, OK, we conjecture
that patients in this subtype
are likely to respond best
to treatment.
So we're only going to
run the clinical trial
for patients in this subtype,
not in the other one.
It might be useful, also,
to try to better understand
the disease mechanism.
So if you find that
there are some people who
seem to progress very
quickly through their disease
and other people who seem
to progress very slowly,
you might then go back and do
new biological assays on them
to try to understand what
differentiates those two
clusters.
So the two clusters
are differentiated
in terms of their
phenotype, but you
want to go back
and ask, well, what
is different about their
genotype that differentiates
them?
And it might also be useful to
have a very concise description
of what differentiates
patients in order
to actually have policies
that you can implement.
So rather than
having what might be
a very complicated linear
model, or even non-linear model,
for predicting future
disease progression,
it would be much easier
if you could just say, OK,
for patients who have
this biomarker abnormal,
they're likely to have very
fast disease progression.
Patients who are likely have
this other biomarker abnormal,
they're likely to have a
slow disease progression.
And so we'd like to
be able to do that.
That's what I mean by
discovering disease subtypes.
But there's actually a second
goal as well, which-- remember,
think back to that original
motivation I mentioned earlier
of having very little data.
If you have very little
data, which is unfortunately
the setting that we're
almost always in when
doing machine learning
in health care,
then you can overfit
really easily to your data
when just using it strictly
within a discriminative
learning framework.
And so if one were to now
change your optimization problem
altogether to start to bring in
an unsupervised loss function,
then one can hope
to get much more
out of the limited data you
have and save the labels, which
you might overfit
on very easily,
for the very last step of
your learning algorithm.
And that's exactly what we'll do
in this segment of the lecture.
So for today, we're
going to think
about the simplest possible
unsupervised learning
algorithm.
And because the official
prerequisite for this course
was 6036, and because clustering
was not discussed in 6036,
I'll spend just
two minutes talking
about clustering using the
simplest algorithm called
K-means, which I hope
almost all of you know.
But this will just
be a simple reminder.
How many clusters are
there in in this figure
that I'm showing over here?
Let's raise some hands.
One cluster?
Two clusters?
Three clusters?
Four clusters?
Five clusters?
OK.
And are these red points
more or less showing
where those five clusters are?
No.
No, they're not.
So rather there's
a cluster here.
There's a cluster here,
there, there, there.
All right.
So you were you are able
to do this really well,
as humans, looking at
two dimensional data.
The goal of algorithms
like K-means
is to show how one could
do that automatically
for high-dimensional data.
And the K-means
algorithm is very simple.
It works as follows.
You hypothesize a
number of clusters.
So here we have
hypothesized five clusters.
You're going to
randomly initialize
those cluster centers,
which I'm denoting
by those red points shown here.
Then in the first stage
of the K-means algorithm,
you're going to assign every
data point to the closest
cluster center.
And that's going to induce
a Voronoi diagram where
every point within
this Voronoi cell
is closer to this red point
than to any other red point.
And so every data point
in this Voronoi cell
will then be assigned
to this data point.
Every data point in
this Voronoi cell
will be assigned to that
data point and so on.
So we're going to now assign
all data points to the closest
cluster center.
And then we're just going
to average all the data
points assigned to
some cluster center
to get the new cluster center.
And you repeat.
And you're going to stop this
procedure when no point in time
is changed.
So let's look at
a simple example.
Here we're using K equals 2.
We just decided there
are only two clusters.
We've initialized the two
clusters shown here, the two
cluster centers, as
this red cluster center
and this blue cluster center.
Notice that they're
nowhere near the data.
We've just randomly chosen.
They're nowhere near the data.
It's actually pretty
bad initialization.
The first step is going
to assign data points
to their closest cluster center.
So I want everyone to say
out loud either red or green,
to which cluster center
it's going to point to,
what it is going to be
assigned to this step.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Red.
Blue.
DAVID SONTAG: All right.
Good.
We get it.
So that's the first assignment.
Now we're going to average the
data points that are assigned
to that red cluster center.
So we're going to average
all the red points.
And the new red cluster center
will be over here, right?
AUDIENCE: No.
DAVID SONTAG: Oh, over there?
Over here?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
DAVID SONTAG: OK.
Good.
And the blue cluster center will
be somewhere over here, right?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
DAVID SONTAG: OK.
Good.
So that's the next step.
And then you repeat.
So now, again, you
assign every data point
to its closest cluster center.
By the way, the
reason why you're
seeing what looks like
a linear hyperplane
here is because there are
exactly two cluster centers.
And then you repeat.
Blah, blah, blah.
And you're done.
So in fact, I think
I've just shown
you the convergence point.
So that's the K-means algorithm.
It's an extremely
simple algorithm.
And what I'm going to
show you for the next 10
minutes of lecture
is how one could
use this very simple clustering
algorithm to better understand
asthma.
So asthma is something
that really affects
a large number of individuals.
It's characterized by having
difficulties breathing.
It's often managed by
inhalers, although, as asthma
gets more and more severe,
you need more and more complex
management schemes.
And it's been found
that 5% to 10%
of people who have severe
asthma remain poorly controlled
despite using the largest
tolerable inhaled therapy.
And so a really
big question that
the pharmaceutical community
is extremely interested in
is, how do we come up with
better therapies for asthma?
There's a lot of
money in that problem.
I first learned
about this problem
when a pharmaceutical
company came to me when
I was a professor
at NYU and asked me,
could they work with
me on this problem?
I said no at the time.
But I still find it interesting.
[CHUCKLING]
And at that time, the
company pointed me
to this paper, which I'll
tell you about in a second.
But before I get there,
I want to point out
what are some of the
big picture questions
that everyone's interested
in when it comes to asthma.
The first one is to
really understand
what is it about either genetic
or environmental factors
that underlie different
subtypes of asthma.
It's observed that
people respond
differently the therapy.
It is observed that some
people aren't even controlled
with therapy.
Why is that?
Third, what are
biomarkers, what are
ways to predict who's
going to respond or not
respond to any one therapy?
And can we get better
mechanistic understanding
of these different subtypes?
And so this was a
long-standing question.
And in this paper from
the American Journal
of Respiratory Critical Care
Medicine, which, by the way,
has a huge number
of citations now--
it's sort of a prototypical
example of subtyping.
That's why I'm going through it.
They started to answer
that question using
a data-driven
approach for asthma.
And what I'm showing you
here is the punch line.
This is that main result, the
main figure over the paper.
They've characterized
asthma in terms
of five different subtypes,
really three type.
One type, which
I'll show over here,
was sort of inflammation
predominant;
one type over there, which
is called early symptom
predominant; and another here,
which is sort of concordant
disease.
And what I'll do over
the next few minutes
is walk you through
how they came up
with these different clusters.
So they used three
different data sets.
These data sets
consisted of patients
who had asthma and already had
at least one recent therapy
for asthma.
They're all nonsmokers.
But they were managed in--
they're three disjoint set
of patients coming from three
different populations.
The first group of
patients were recruited
from primary care practices
in the United Kingdom.
All right.
So if you're a
patient with asthma,
and your asthma is being managed
by your primary care doctor,
then it's probably not too bad.
But if your asthma,
on the other hand,
were being managed at a
refractory asthma clinic, which
is designed specifically for
helping patients manage asthma,
then your asthma is
probably a bit more severe.
And that second group of
patients, 187 patients,
were from that second cohort
of patients managed out
of an asthma clinic.
The third data set is much
smaller, only 68 patients.
But it's very
unique because it is
coming from a 12-month study,
where it was a clinical trial,
and there were two different
types of treatments applied
given to these patients.
And it was a randomized
control trial.
So the patients were
randomized into each
of the two arms of the study.
I'll describe to you
what the features
are on just the next slide.
But first I want to
tell you about how
their pre-processes to use
within the K-means algorithm.
Continuous-valued features
where z-scored in order
to normalize their ranges.
And categorical variables
were represented just
by a one-hot encoding.
Some of the continuous
variables were furthermore
transformed prior to
clustering by taking
the logarithm of the features.
And that's something that
can be very useful when
doing something like K-means.
Because it can, in essence,
allow for that Euclidean
distance function,
which is using K-means,
to be more meaningful
by capturing
more of a dynamic
range of the feature.
So these were the features
that went into the clustering
algorithm.
And there are very, very few,
so roughly 20, 30 features.
They range from the
patient's gender and age
to their body mass index, to
measures of their function,
to biomarkers such as
eosinophil count that
could be measured from the
patient's sputum, and more.
And there a couple of
other features that I'll
show you later as well.
And you could look to see
how did these quantities, how
did these populations, differ.
So on this column, you see
the primary care population.
You look at all of these
features in that population.
You see that in the
primary care population,
the individuals are-- on
average, 54% percent of them
are female.
In the secondary care
population, 65% of them
are female.
You notice that
things like-- if you
look at to some measures
of lung function,
it's significantly worse in
that secondary care population,
as one would expect.
Because these are patients
with more severe asthma.
So next, after doing
K-means clustering,
these are the three
clusters that result.
And now I'm showing you
the full set of features.
So let me first tell
you how to read this.
This is clusters found in
the primary care population.
This column here is
just the average values
of those features across
the full population.
And then for each one
of these three clusters,
I'm showing you
the average value
of the corresponding feature
in just that cluster.
And in essence, that's exactly
the same as those red points
I was showing you
when I describe to you
K-means clustering.
It's the cluster center.
And one could also look
at the standard deviation
of how much variance
there is along
that feature in that cluster.
And that's what the numbers in
parentheses are telling you.
So the first thing to note
is that in Cluster 1, which
the authors of the study named
Early Onset Atopic Asthma,
these are very young patients,
average of 14, 15 years old,
as opposed to Cluster 2,
where the average age was
35 years old-- so a
dramatic difference there.
Moreover, we see that these are
patients who have actually been
to the hospital recently.
So most of these patients
have been to the hospital.
On average, these patients have
been to hospital at least once
recently.
And furthermore, they've had
severe asthma exacerbations
in the past 12 months, at least,
on average, twice per patient.
And those are very large
numbers relative to what you
see in these other clusters.
So that's really
describing something
that's very unusual about these
very young patients with pretty
severe asthma.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: What is the
p-value [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID SONTAG: Yeah.
I think the p-value--
I don't know if this is
a pair-wise comparison.
I don't remember off
the top of my head.
But it's really looking at the
difference between, let's say--
I don't know which of these cl--
I don't know if it's
comparing two of them or not.
But let's say, for
example, it might
be looking at the difference
between this and that.
But I'm just hypothesizing.
I don't remember.
Cluster 2, one other hand,
was predominately female.
So 81% of the patients
were female there.
And they were
largely overweight.
So their average body mass
index was 36, as opposed
to the other two clusters,
where the average body mass
index was 26.
And Cluster 3 consisted of
patients who really have not
had that severe asthma.
So the average number of
previous hospital admissions
and asthma exacerbations
was dramatically smaller
than in the other two clusters.
So this is the result
of the finding.
And then you might
ask, well, how
does that generalize to
the other two populations?
So they then went to the
secondary care population.
And they reran the clustering
algorithm from scratch.
And this is a completely
disjoint set of patients.
And what they found,
what they got out,
is that the first
two clusters exactly
resembled Clusters 1 and
2 from the previous study
on the primary care population.
But because this is a different
population with much more
severe patients, that
third cluster earlier
of benign asthma doesn't show
up in this new population.
And there are two
new clusters that
show up in this new population.
So the fact that those
first two clusters
were consistent across two
very different populations
gave the authors
confidence that there
might be something real here.
And then they went and they
explored that third population,
where they had
longitudinal data.
And that third population
they were then using to ask,
does it not-- so
up until now, we've
only used baseline information.
But now we're going to ask
the following question.
If we took the baseline
data from those 68 patients
and we were to separate them
into three different clusters
based on the characterizations
found in the other two data
sets, and then if
we were to look
at long-term outcomes
for each cluster,
would they be different
across the clusters?
And in particular,
here we actually looked
at not just predicting
a progression,
but we're also looking
at prediction--
we're looking at differences
in treatment response.
Because this was a
randomized-control trial.
And so there are going to
be two arms here, what's
called the clinical arm, which
is the standard clinical care,
and what's called the
sputum arm, which consists
of doing regular monitoring
of the airway inflammation,
and then tight trading
steroid therapy
in order to maintain
normal eosinophil counts.
And so this is comparing two
different treatment strategies.
And the question is, do these
two treatment strategies result
in differential outcomes?
So when the clinical trial was
originally performed and they
computed the average treatment
effect, which, by the way,
because the RCT was
particularly simple--
you just averaged outcomes
across the two arms--
they found that there was no
difference across the two arms.
So there was no difference
in outcomes across the two
different therapies.
Now what these authors
are going to do
is they're going
to rerun the study.
And they're going to now,
instead of just looking
at the average treatment effect
for the whole population,
they're going to use--
they're going to look at
the average treatment each
of the clusters by themselves.
And the hope there
is that one might
be able to see now a
difference, maybe that there
was heterogeneous
treatment response
and sometimes that therapy
worked for some people
and not for others.
And these were the results.
So indeed, across
these three clusters,
we see actually a
very big difference.
So if you look
here, for example,
the number of commenced
on oral corticosteroids,
which is a measure
of an outcome--
so you might want this to--
I can't remember,
small or large.
But there was a big difference
between these two clusters.
And this cluster, the number
commenced under the first arm
is two; in this other
cluster for patients
who got the second arm, nine;
and exactly the opposite
for this third cluster.
The first cluster, by the way,
had only three patients in it.
So I'm not going to make
any comment about it.
Now, since these go in
completely opposite directions,
it's not surprising that
the average treatment
effect across the whole
population was zero.
But what we're seeing now
is that, in fact, there
is a difference.
And so it's possible
that the therapy
is actually effective but just
for a smaller number of people.
Now, this study would've never
been possible had we not done
this clustering beforehand.
Because it has so few
patients, only 68 patients.
If you attempted to both
search for the clustering
at the same time
as, let's say, find
clusters to
differentiate outcomes,
you would overfit the
data very quickly.
So it's precisely because we
did this unsupervised sub-typing
first, and then
use the labels not
for searching for the subtypes
but only for evaluating
the subtypes, that
we're actually
able to do something
interesting here.
So in summary, in
today's lecture,
I talked about two
different approaches,
a supervised approach
for predicting
future disease status and
an unsupervised approach.
And there were a few
major limitations
that I want to
emphasize that we'll
return to in the next
lecture and try to address.
The first major
limitation is that none
of these approaches
differentiated between disease
stage and subtype.
In both of the
two approaches, we
assumed that there were
some amount of alignment
of patients at baseline.
For example, here we assume
that the patients at time zero
were somewhat
similar to another.
For example, they
might have been
newly diagnosed with Alzheimer's
at that point in time.
But often we have
a data set where
we have no natural
alignment of patients
in terms of disease stage.
And if we attempted to do
some type of clustering
like I did in this last
example, what you would get out,
naively, would be one
cluster for disease stage.
So patients who are very
early in their disease stage
might look very different
from patients who are
late in their disease stage.
And it will completely
conflate disease stage
from disease subtype, which
is what you might actually
want to discover.
The second limitation
of these approaches
is that they only used one
time point per patient,
whereas in reality,
such as you saw here,
we might have
multiple time points.
And we might want
to, for example,
do clustering using
multiple time points.
Or we might want to
use multiple time
points to understand something
about disease progression.
The third limitation
is that they
assume that there
is a single factor,
let's say disease subtype,
that explained all variation
in the patients.
In fact, there might
be other factors,
patient-specific factors,
that one would like
to use in your noise model.
When you use an algorithm
like K-means for clustering,
it presents no opportunity
for doing that,
because it has such a
naive distance function.
And so in next
week's lecture, we're
going to move in
to start talking
a probabilistic modeling
approaches to these problems,
which will give us a very
natural way of characterizing
variation along other axes.
And finally, a natural
question you should ask
is, does it have to be
unsupervised or supervised?
Or is there a way to combine
those two approaches.
All right.
We'll get back to
that on Tuesday.
That's all.